Rosa Paula Cuevas, PhD

1354 Emerson Drive • Pittsburg, California 94565 • Mobile: 925.844.4768 rochiecuevas@gmail.com • LinkedIn: rosa-paula-cuevas

PROFILE

A competent, skilled, and focus-driven professional with 15 years of experience and a strong record of achievement in **food science** and **data analysis** in the international development space.

Extensive background of experience in working in multidisciplinary teams.

English (fluent); Filipino (fluent, native speaker); French (beginner)

Effective communication with technical and non-technical audiences.

SPECIALIZED SKILLS

- Data analyses: R and Python
- Scientific writing and communication
- Food science: sensory science, cereal chemistry, grain quality evaluation

PROFESSIONAL RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2004-2018

INTERNATIONAL RICE RESEARCH INSTITUTE (IRRI), Philippines Grain Quality and Nutrition Center

Scientist (2015-2018)

- Generated insights from data generated through metabolomics, sensory evaluation, rheometry, and cereal chemistry, leading towards peer-reviewed journal articles, extension presentations, and popular media.
- Developed insights about context-specific and culture-sensitive food consumption and preference
 patterns using the "gastronomic systems research framework", co-developed with economists and
 market researchers.
- Headed, mentored, and managed IRRI's sensory evaluation team.

Consultant (2014–2015)

 Developed rice product profiles through sensory evaluation, instrumental texture profile analyses, and rheometry.

Postdoctoral Fellow (2010–2014)

- Established the Grain Quality and Nutrition Center sensory evaluation team, a research group composed of staff who I trained in difference and in descriptive sensory techniques.
- Communicated stories and insights from data generated in various technical and non-technical fora.

Professional Service Staff (2008–2010)

 Developed databases for full-cost recovery work packages of the Grain Quality and Nutrition Center's quality evaluation service facility.

Researcher (2004–2005)

Conducted initial studies characterizing rice starches using the following laboratory equipment:

- differential scanning calorimeter
- rheometer
- · fluorophore-assisted capillary electrophoreses
- size-exclusion chromatography

2002-2003

RESEARCHER, INTERNATIONAL RICE RESEARCH INSTITUTE

Plant Breeding, Genetics, and Biotechnology Division

- Genotyped japonica rice utilizing simple sequence repeat (SSR) and restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) molecular markers to locate the putative gene for low-tillering rice plant type.
- Trained staff and students in conducting polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and agarose gel electrophoresis.

Rosa Paula Cuevas, PhD

1354 Emerson Drive • Pittsburg, California 94565 • Mobile: 925.844.4768 rochiecuevas@gmail.com • LinkedIn: rosa-paula-cuevas

ADDITIONAL RESEARCH BACKGROUND

Peer-reviewer for the following scientific journals:

African Journal of Biotechnology

Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry

International Rice Research Notes

Carbohydrate Polymers

African Journal of Food Science

· Czech Journal of Genetics and Plant Breeding

SEAMEO Biotrop

Field Crops Research

Global Change Biology

British Food Journal

BMC Ecology

EDUCATION

Data Analytics and Visualization (2018–present)

UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, BERKELEY EXTENSION

PhD Agricultural Science (2005–2009)

UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, Australia

Thesis: Starch microstructure and functional properties in waxy rice (Oryza sativa L.)

Concentration: Starch structure, cereal chemistry, rice

Bachelor of Science - Biology, Magna cum Laude (1998–2002)

UNIVERSITY OF THE PHILIPPINES LOS BAÑOS, Philippines

Concentration: Microbiology

MEMBERSHIPS AND AFFILIATIONS

- Student Member, American Association of Cereal Chemistry International (2005, 2008)
- Life Member, Philippine Society for Microbiology, Inc.
- Life Member, Phi Sigma Honor Society for Biology (Alpha Chi Chapter, University of the Philippines
- Member, Gamma Sigma Delta Honor Society of Agriculture
- Member, Phi Kappa Phi Honor Society (University of the Philippines Chapter)

ACADEMIC HONORS AND AWARDS

- SDG Talent, UNLEASH Innovations Laboratory, Denmark, 2017
- Panelist, 20th Japan Science and Technology Agency Anniversary Forum and Science Agora, Japan, 2016
- Young Scientist Fellow, Nestlé Conference, 2015
- Gawad Lagunense (Youth Category), 2010
- Poster Paper Competition Award, 4th International Meeting on Starch Structure and Functionality, United Kingdom, 2008
- C&E Student Travel Booster to the American Association of Cereal Chemistry International Annual Meeting, USA, 2008
- Bank of the Philippine Islands Science Award, Philippine, 2002
- UPLB College of Arts and Science Outstanding Student Award, Philippines, 2001

CERTIFICATIONS

- Foundation in Pastry Arts, International School for Culinary Arts and Hotel Management, Philippines, 2013
- Foundation in Culinary Arts, International School for Culinary Arts and Hotel Management, Philippines, 2013
- Microbiologist, Philippine Academy of Microbiology, 2003